ATHM Textile Industry Stereographs 6524/006 P
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
- Series II: General Images Organized by Textile Related Subject
  - Fiber Preparation (Box 8, Folder 4)
    - Item 46: Weighing Basket of Freshly Picked Cotton in the Field (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Black-and-white image of two male workers in a field, holding a basket of cotton on a pole and using a hand-held scale to weigh it. Several workers look on. The two men on the left taking notes appear to be white, everyone else is African American. A man stands and watches from a wagon filled with baskets of cotton. Stenciled on the wagon is "Made for W. A. Potts Newnan, Ga." Pay for picking the cotton was about one half cent per pound. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company, copyright, Underwood & Underwood, ca. 1900-1920. 17.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 47: The Machine that Separates Lint Cotton from the Seed (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Black-and-white image of an African American male operating a cotton gin inside of a brick building. Prior to the invention of Eli Whitney's cotton gin, cotton was a difficult crop to work with and thus was not very popular in the United States. After the invention of the cotton gin, however, cotton became much easier to work with and more profitable, and many southern planters reversed their position on slavery, wanting more slaves to work with their cotton crops. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company, ca. 1900-1920. 17.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 48: Shaping and Putting in Press Boiled Kernels of Cotton-seed to Extract Oil (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Black-and-white image of two male African American workers using presses and a cake former to extract cottonseed oil from cooked cottonseed cakes. The worker in the foreground can be seen using the cake former, and the worker in the background can be seen using the hydraulic press. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company, ca. 1900-1920. 17.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 49: Pressing Oil from the Cooked Cotton-seed; Boiler in Background (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Black-and-white image of an African American male worker putting cloth-covered cottonseed cakes into the hydraulic press. Once all of the press shelves are filled, cottonseed oil is squeezed out of the cakes, runs down the side of the press, and flows through a trough to a settling tank. It takes about 20 minutes to fill the shelves of the press, extract oil, and empty the shelves for refilling. Note the boiler in the right background. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company, ca. 1900-1920. 17.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 50: Taking Cakes of Cotton-seed Meal from Press, which Extracts the Oil (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Black-and-white image of two African American males removing cottonseed cakes from a press and stripping the cloths off them. Cottonseed cakes are placed into the press to remove the oil. Cottonseed cakes were sold as stock feed, and when ground up, they became cottonseed meal. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Company, ca. 1900-1920. 17.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 51: Ocean S. S. Co.'s Cotton Yard, Savannah, Georgia, 1905 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Black- and-white image depicts a large cotton yard filled with cotton bales. Some buildings in the background on the right. Dated on the card September 9, 1905. H. Hymes, Art Store, Savannah, Ga. [photographer?] Raphael Tuck & Sons' Post Card Series No. 1010, "Savannah." Art Publishers to their Majesties the King and Queen. 13.75 x 9 cm.
    - Item 52: Cotton Awaiting Shipment (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of the interior of a large cotton shed. The floor is covered in cotton bales. Several male workers can be seen standing and/or laying on the bales. A horse-drawn wagon is visible to the right of the shed. Location unknown. "Phostint" Card, made only by Detroit Publishing Co. ca. 1915-1924. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 53: A Truckload of Cotton in Dixieland (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of red flatbed truck filled with stacks of cotton bales. Three male workers are standing in front of the truck, which is parked on the side of a tree-lined street. Published by Asheville Post Card Co., Asheville, N.C. Dated and postmarked March 1, 1950, Daytona Beach, Fla., but the card was probably manufactured before 1944. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 54: Cotton seed delivered at mill where oil is extracted, Georgia, U.S.A. (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Black-and-white image of two African American male workers, one standing on the ground and one on a platform, shoveling cotton seed into elevated doorways at a mill. Piles of cotton seed can be seen in the photo, both in doorways and on the ground. New York: Underwood & Underwood, ca. 1900-1910. 17.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 55: "Down upon the Mississippi", 1907 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of a packet floating down the Mississippi River, piled high with cotton bales. Workers can be seen standing both on the top of the cotton bales and on a small platform on the lower part of the front of the boat. Printed on the reverse of the card: " 'Down upon the Mississippi.' The packets plying the Mississippi River measure 50 feet from keel to root of upper cabin; their average length is 250 feet, with a carrying capacity of a thousand tons. The main deck is occupied by boilers, machinery and freight; above, is the saloon with commodious staterooms, while a third story contains the officers' quarters. 136 landings are made between Memphis and New Orleans." Raphael Tuck and Sons' Post Card Series No. 2384 "Under Southern Skies." Printed in Germany. Dated March 17, 1907. See also Item 58, in this folder, for basically the same image. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 56: Cotton on the Levee, Memphis, Tennessee (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of several large boats docked at a levee. The land near the dock has many cotton bales, as well as various other sacks. Workers are seen standing and sitting on and near the cotton bales and boats. Photograph courtesy Chamber of Commerce, Memphis, Tenn. Sold by Bluff City News Co., Memphis, Tenn. A "Colourpicture" Publication, Boston 15, Mass. ca. 1943-1945. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 57: Transportation of Cotton by Rail (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of numerous flatbed traincars on a track, loaded with bales of cotton. Male workers are standing and sitting on top of the bales. ca. 1907-1915. 14 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 58: Transportation of Cotton by River (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of a packet floating in a river. The boat is piled high with cotton bales. Workers can be seen standing on top of the cotton bales, and also on a platform on the lower part of the front of the boat. ca. 1907-1915. See also Item 55, in this folder, for basically the same image with some explanation of Mississippi River packets. 13.5 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 59: Levee Scene and Water Front, Loading Cotton, Memphis, Tennessee (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of a male worker sitting on a bale of cotton on the waterfront. The ground behind the worker is covered with cotton bales. A boat can be seen floating down the river in the background. Bluff City News Co., Memphis, Tenn. "C.T. Art-Colortone" made only by Curt Teich & Co., Inc., Chicago. ca. 1930-1944. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 60: Transportation of Cotton by River (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of a packet boat in a river, piled high with cotton bales. A large number of workers can be seen sitting and standing on top of the bales and on a platforn at the lower part of the front of the boat. The riverbank is visible in the background of the image. Adolf Selige Pub. Co., St. Louis--Leipzig. Printed in Germany. ca. 1907-1915. 13.5 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 61: Cotton Transportation by Road (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Black-and-white image of a man sitting atop a wagon piled with cotton bales three rows high. The wagon is being pulled by at least four mules. A few other people on horseback and several buildings are visible along the street in the background of the image. ca. 1902-1907. 14 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 62: Rolling Cotton Down the Bluff, 1911 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of African American workers rolling cotton bales down a bluff to be loaded on the waiting steamer. Some workers stand near a large group of cotton bales at the top of the bluff, while others are in the midst of rolling bales down the bluff. Printed on reverse of card: "Rolling cotton down the bluff. This picture shows the negroes rolling the cotton down the bluff to be loaded on the waiting steamer. The average bale weighs 500 pounds. One hundred years ago it would have taken a person working night and day two years to separate the seed from the cotton in one bale; to-day a battery ginnery has a capacity of 155 hundred pound bales in welve hours." Raphael Tuck & Sons' Post Card Series No. 2370, "In the Land of Cotton." Printed in Germany. Postmarked April 26, 1911, but card was manufactured before 1908. 14 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 63: Mecklenburg County Roads near Charlotte, N.C. (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of two views of Mecklenburg County roads. In the top image, a car holding several men and women is driving on the road near a bridge, and a horse-drawn wagon is barely visible in the background. In the bottom image, a horse (or mule)-drawn wagon piled high with cotton bales travels on a road, behind several wagons pulling smaller loads of other items. Published by S.H. Kress & Co. Made in U.S.A. ca. 1907-1915. 8.5 x 13.75 cm.
    - Item 64: Off to Market, 1909 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of open, flatbed railroad cars loaded with bales of cotton. Other train tracks and traincars and buildings are visible in the background of the image. Raphael Tuck & Sons' Series No. 2653, "From Southern Soil." Photochromed in Saxony. Dated April 18, 1909 but not postmarked. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 65: Train Loads of Cotton for Export, 1915 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of traincars on a track, some open flatbed cars, loaded high with bales of cotton. The car in the foreground has six rows of bales piled high, not counting what cannot be seen within the sides of the car. "Phostint" made only by Detroit Publishing Co. Postmarked May 17, 1915, Southern Pines, N.C. 14 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 66: A Typical Cotton Cart (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of a horse-drawn cotton cart loaded with four cotton bales. The cart appears in front of a brick building, and an African American man holds the reins. "Phostint" card made only by Detroit Publishing Co. ca. 1915-1924. 14 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 67: Commercial Scene in Harbor, Washington, N.C., 1909 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Sepia- tinted image of a docked boat filled with cotton bales. A group of men, almost all wearing three-piece suits and hats, sit and stand on the bales. In the background, men can be seen loading cotton bales onto the boat. Photo only copyright by F.S.W. Made in Germany. Dated on reverse December 29, 1909. 13.5 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 68: Steamer Loading Cotton at State Docks, Mobile, Alabama, 1940 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of cotton bales being loaded by workers onto steamer ships at the state docks. Some bales are being loaded via ramp, while others are being lifted with ropes. A concrete warehouse is visible on the left side of the image. Printed on reverse of card: "Cargoes of cotton for shipment to European Ports are accumulated in the huge concrete fireproof warehouse and then loaded aboard after being compressed, by the ship's tackle. Southward, on both sides of the river can be seen the dry docks and shipbuilding plants, fish and oyster docks, and many other interesting sights." Made in U.S.A. by E.C. Kropp Co., Milwaukee, Wis. Postmarked May 21, 1940, in Mexboro, Ala. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 69: The Land of Cotton, 1896 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Black-and-white image of workers standing with bales of cotton in front of a shed. Several brick buildings are visible in the background. The back of the stereograph contains an advertisement for The American Tobacco company, based in the Green River District of Kentucky. Elisabeth, N.J.: Alfred S. Campbell. 17.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 70: Shipping cotton from levee near growing district by cars to manufacturing centre, Texas (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Black-and- white image of African American workers loading bales of cotton onto railroad cars to be shipped to a manufacturing center. The workers are using dollies to transport the heavy bales into the cars, on the right side of the image. On the left side of the image, the ground is covered with bales, upon one of which two men stand, one of whom (holding papers in his hand) is the overseer. New York: Underwood & Underwood, ca. 1900-1920. 17.75 x 8.75 cm. Copy B.
    - Item 71: Loading Cotton, Savannah, Georgia, 1908 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Black-and-white image of bales of cotton covering the ground, with railroad cars in the background and what appear to be the masts of boats behind them. There are several sheds visible on the right side of the image, and workers can be seen moving bales of cotton and walking about throughout the image. Pub. by J.S. Pinkussohn Cigar Co., Savannah, Ga. Made in Germany. Postmarked November 11, 1908 in Savannah. 14 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 72: Loading Cotton at Houston, Texas (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of a docked ship with ramps from ship to dock. Workers can be seen at the bottom of the ramps, using dollies to transport bales of cotton. Published by Seawall Specialty Co., Houston and Galveston, Texas. C.T. American Art Colored. ca. 1915-1930. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 73: A Record Breaking Load of Cotton, Memphis, Tennessee (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of a large load of cotton, piled about ten bales high, on a docked boat. Workers can be seen standing at the front of the boat, atop the cotton, and on the dock. ca. 1907-1915. 8.75 x 13.5 cm.
    - Item 74: Loading Cotton into Ship's Hold (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of bales of cotton being lowered by rope into the hold of a ship. Several men are holding onto the ropes and the bales as they are being lowered. Another man stands and watches, while yet another operates machinery in the background. "Phostint" made only by Detroit Publishing Co. ca. 1915-1924. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 75: Macon, Georgi+G1125a, Poplar St. Looking South, 1905 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of a street, surrounded by buildings on both sides, which is almost completely covered by rows of cotton bales. Horse-drawn wagons and pedestrians are seen traveling on the street using a narrow path on the right side of the image. Raphael Tuck & Sons' Post Card Series No. 2074 "Macon, Ga." Dated on the bottom of the card September 11, 1905. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 76: Hauling Cotton to Market (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of men driving two horse-drawn wagons, each loaded with cotton bales, along a tree-lined dirt road. Location is unknown. C.T. Photocrom. ca. 1907-1915. 13.5 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 77: Handling Cotton at Wharves, Norfolk, Virginia (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of male workers working with bags of cotton. A dolly and baskets are on the ground near the workers; many bags cover the ground behind the workers. I. Stern, New York. Made in Germany. 1907-1915. 13.5 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 78: Shipping Cotton, Savannah, Georgia (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of many bales of cotton in front of docks. The masts of several ships are visible in the background. Several more bales are lined up in the grass in the foreground of the image. Illustrated Post Card Co., N.Y. 1902-1907. 14 cm x 9 cm.
    - Item 79: Shipping Cotton, 1906 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of workers loading cotton bales onto a ship for export. One worker can be seen at the front of a row of bales, moving a bale up a ramp onto the ship. Other workers can be seen using a dolly to move a bale. Printed on reverse of card: "Shipping cotton. Three-fourths of the cotton supply of the world is grown in the U.S.; in 1905, 7,000,000 bales were exported. Standard bales weigh 500 pounds; if they are to be shipped any great distance, they are reduced to one-third their bulk by secondary presses, and thus compressed, are forced into the holds of the ships by jackscrews in order to occupy as little space as possible." Raphael Tuck & Sons' Post Card Series No. 2384 "Under Soiuthern Skies." Postmarked September [2], 1906, in Savannah, Ga., and Sept. 3, 1906 in Chicopee Falls, Mass. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 80: Shipping Cotton, Vicksburg, Mississippi (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of a busy scene, with African American workers moving bags and bales of cotton on a crowded dock. Several ships, some loaded with cotton bales, are visible on the left side of the image. Printed on reverse of card: "Loading cotton: Husky, singing negroes handle these great bales of cotton as most people would handle bed pillows. On the great Mississippi river, packets and barges are piled high with the billowy white cotton, tightly encased in burlap wrappings." Made in U.S. A. by E.C. Kropp Co., Milwaukee, Wis. ca. 1930-1944. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 81: Barge Load of Cotton on River Front, New Orleans, Louisiana (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of a dock, where workers load bales of cotton onto barges. Workers can be seen moving bales into place on the barge, as well as standing near the entrance of a warehouse on the dock. Made in U.S. A. by E.C. Kropp Co., Milwaukee, Wis. ca. 1930-1944. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 82: Steamer loading cotton, New Orleans, Louisian+G1129a, 1906 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of workers on a dock, loading bales of cotton onto a steamer using a ramp. Some workers use dollies to move the bales on the dock, while others wait on the steamer. The Rotograph Co., N.Y. City. [Made in] Germany. Dated May 1, 1906; postmarked May 1 in New Orleans, and May 3, in Boston, Mass. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 83: Mississippi River Steamboat Loaded with Cotton, New Orleans, Louisiana (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of a steamboat in the Mississippi River, close to the riverbank, loaded with cotton. The bales appear to be stacked at least twelve rows high. Many men can be seen, both standing on the riverbank and standing on various parts of the steamboat. Scordill, Publisher, 902 Canal St., New Orleans, La. A. D. Lytle, Photographer. ca. 1907-1915. 13.5 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 84: Hauling Cotton to Gin (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of a male worker driving a mule-drawn wagon loaded with cotton through a field. A small building is visible to the left of the worker, and an unmanned wagon is visible slightly further up the path. T.P. & Co., N.Y. ca. 1907-1915. 13.5 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 85: Shipping Cotton, Mobile, Alabama (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of a busy dock scene. The dock is loaded with cotton, and several male workers are seen standing near and carrying large sacks. Steamships are lined up at the docks, some with cotton on board. Made in U.S.A. by E.C. Kropp Co., Milwaukee. ca. 1915-1930. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 86: Cotton Market, Broad Street, Rome, Georgia, 1908 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of a busy cotton market scene taking place on a street lined with brick buildings. The street is filled with wagons loaded with cotton, and people are standing and walking throughout the market. Published by The American News Company, New York. Leipzig, Berlin and Dresden. Postmarked April 13, 1908. 13.5 x 9 cm.
    - Item 87: Cotton on its way to market, Port of Stockton, California (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of a docked ship with the name "Luckenbach" painted on the side. On land, next to the ship, are rows of cotton bales and several cranes. Printed on reverse of the card: "Cotton, California's #1 field crop, at the Port of Stockton on its way to market. California ranks fourth in the production of cotton and has the highest yield per acre of any state. Practically all of the present cotton acreage is in the San Joaquin Valley." Union Oil Company's Natural Color Scenes of the West. Made in U.S.A. ca. 1950s. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 88: River barges laden with the crop of Texas cotton fields, the finest in the world, 1905 (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Black-and-white image of two river barges, one with the name "Hercules of Lake Charles" visible on the edge of the stern, loaded with cotton. Several buildings are visible on the land next to the barges, and the yard in the background of the image has rows of cotton bales. Workers can be seen handling rope on the barges. Title is printed on the back in English, French, German, Spanish, Swedish, and Russian. New York: Underwood & Underwood. 17.75 x 8.75 cm. Copy B.
    - Item 89: Transportation of cotton by road (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of a street lined with buildings and trees. Several wagons loaded with cotton are lined up on one side of the street; another can be seen on the other side of the street. In the background, a pile of cotton bales is visible on the left side of the street. Location is unknown. Adolph Selige Pub. Co., St. Louis--Leipzig. ca. 1902-1907. 13.5 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 90: Cotton Pickers Returning from the Field (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of five African American cotton workers, three males and two females, one of whom is a child, with a horse-drawn wagon loaded with baskets of cotton. A dirt road and house are visible in the background. Location is unknown. E.C. Kropp, Publ., Milwaukee. ca. 1907. 14 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 91: Cotton Scene, Galveston, Texas (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of a railroad yard filled with rows of cotton bales, some of which are being loaded onto the railroad cars that are lined up at the back of the yard. On one train car, the letters "S.A. & A.P." are visible. In the background, city buildings can be seen. Published by International Post Card Co., New York. Made in Germany. ca. 1907-1915. 13.5 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 92: Scene on the Levee, Memphis, Tennessee (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of a busy dock, loaded with rows of sacks and bales of cotton. Workers are seen throughout the image, some carrying sacks. Steamers are lined up at the dock, some loaded with cotton bales. Postmarked May 21, 191- [date is blurred with ink]. 14 x 9 cm.
    - Item 93: Cotton Warehouse, Savannah, Georgia (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Color image of the interior of a cotton warehouse filled with bales of cotton. Two male workers, one African American, are seen holding bits of cotton in their hands. Other workers are visible looking at cotton bales in the background. Published by the Valentine & Sons Publishing Co., Ltd., New York and Atlanta, Ga. Printed in Great Britain. ca. 1907-1915. 13.5 x 8.5 cm.
    - Item 94: Cotton! Cotton! Cotton! Levee, New Orleans, La. (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Black-and-white image of a levee scene in which the ground is covered in rows of cotton bales. Workers can be seen laying and standing on the cotton bales and walking about the levee; the two workers laying on the bales in the foreground are African American. In the background, two large river steamers are visible. The cotton bales have been unloaded from river steamers, and will be loaded onto ocean-going vessels and transported to other states and countries. Meadville, Pa.: Keystone View Comany, ca. 1900-1920. 17.75 x 8.75 cm.
    - Item 95: Shipping cotton from levee near growing district by cars to manufacturing centre, Texas (Box 8, Folder 4)
      Black-and- white image of African American workers loading bales of cotton onto railroad cars to be shipped to a manufacturing center. The workers are using dollies to transport the heavy bales into the cars, on the right side of the image. On the left side of the image, the ground is covered with bales, upon one of which two men stand, one of whom (holding papers in his hand) is the overseer. New York: Underwood & Underwood, ca. 1900-1920. 17.75 x 8.75 cm. Copy A.
    - Item 96: Wharf Loading Cotton, Memphis, Tennessee (Box 8, Folder 4)